Finding Aid for the Collection of Sheet Music, circa 1790-1950
State University of New York at Buffalo. Music Library
- Kleber, Henry, 1816-1897 Rainbow schottisch Rainbow schottisch, 1864, 1 score (5 pages); Boston (Mass.): Oliver Ditson and Co. For piano. 120th edition. Color title page illustration: a man and two women viewing a rainbow / lithographed by N.E. Lith. Steam. (Box 2, Item 55)
  Bound with: Jolly brothers galop / F. Budik (Newburgh, New York: Demorest and Burr) -- Gertrude's dream: waltz / Beethoven (New York: Wm. A. Pond and Co., plate no. 1762)
- Klickmann, F. Henri (Frank Henri), 1885-1966 Hesitation waltz Hesitation waltz: the last waltz together, 1923, 1 score (7 pages); Chicago (Ill.): Frank K. Root and Co. For piano. Other title: Valse Boston At head of title page: "Valse Boston". Color title page illustration: scene of a couple dancing in a ballroom, with a floral border. (Box 2, Item 56)
- Lampe, J. B. (Jens Bodewalt), 1869-1929 Hero of the isthmus Hero of the isthmus: military march and two-step, 1912, 1 score (5 pages); New York (N.Y.): Jerome H. Remick and Co. For piano. Dedicated to Col. George W. Goethals, Chief Engineer of The Panama Canal. Color title page illustration: a photographic portrait of Col. George W. Goethals, flanked by two men in USA military uniforms / Clinedinst. (Box 2, Item 57)
- Lauder, Harry, Sir, 1870-1950 She is my rosie She is my rosie, 1915, 1 score (5 pages); New York (N.Y.): T. B. Harms and Francis, Day and Hunter For voice and piano. Lyricist: Harper, J. D. Music includes written text for patter (spoken after 1st verse) and dialogue (spoken after 1st chorus). Notes that the piece was originally sung by Harry Lauder. Color title page illustration: photographic portrait of Harry Lauder in costume. (Box 2, Item 58)
- Leduc, A. (Alphonse), 1804-1868 Jenny of the mill Jenny of the mill, between 1845-1898, 1 score (7 pages); London (England): Robert, Cocks and Co. For voice and piano. Lyricist: Linley, George, 1798-1865 Notes that the piece was originally sung by Madme. Lemmens Sherrington. Color title page illustration: a young woman in a red skirt sitting outside of a mill / S. Rosenthal (Box 2, Item 59)
- Liszt, Franz, 1811-1886 Liebestraum; arranged Liebestraum = Dream of love, 1940, 1 score (9 pages); New York (N.Y.): Amsco Music Publishing Co. For voice and piano. Lyricist: Whitehall, Michel Other title: Dream of love At head of title page: Amsco elite series Color title page illustration: a branch of flowers and leaves / illustrated by Barbelle. (Box 2, Item 60)
- Mack, Edward, 1826-1882 General Grant's grand march General Grant's grand march, 1862, 1 score (5 pages); Philadelphia (Pa.): Lee and Walker For piano. Title page illustration: a portrait of General Ulysses S. Grant in military uniform / lithographed by T. Sinclair's. (Box 2, Item 61)
  Bound with: Grand march, illustrative of Stonewall Jackson's way / Chas. Young (New York: J. L. Peters, 1864) (portrait by Endicott and Co. Lith.)
- Marschner, Heinrich, 1795-1861 Juchheissa. English Hurrah = Juchheissa, 1883, 1 score (7 pages); Buffalo (N.Y.): August Rottenbach For voice and piano. Lyricist: Underwood, Laura M. Lyrics in German and English (by Laura M. Underwood). "The Morning and Evening Musicale: A choice collection of songs carefully edited and selected for use in the Concert-hall and Parlor." (Box 2, Item 62)
- Masquelie, V. Amica polka Amica polka, undated, 1 score (5 pages); Paris (France): Bonoldi Frères For piano. Dedicated to Pauline Fauvel. Title page illustration: two women sitting together / lithographed by Bertauts. (Box 2, Item 63)
- Millard, H. (Harrison), 1830-1895 Waiting Waiting: song for soprano or tenor, 1867, 1 score (7 pages); New York (N.Y.): Unidentified For voice and piano. Lyricist: Flagg, E. H. (Ellen H.) "Compliments of HM"--possible inscription by the composer on title page. Back cover: "List of some of H. Millard's recent compositions". Color title page illustration: a woman standing amidst a field of hay lined with trees / engraved, lithographed and printed by C. O. Clayton. (Box 2, Item 64)
- Miller, Fred (Composer) I have no mother now I have no mother now: ballad, 1858, 1 score (5 pages); Buffalo (N.Y.): Blodgett and Bradford For voice and piano. Notes that the piece was originally sung by Miss Hattie Brown. Dedicated to Miss N. M. Andrus of Buffalo. Title page illustration: title text illuminated by filigree. (Box 2, Item 65)
- Miné, Jacques Claude Adolphe, 1796-1854 Fouyous. Faucheux Fouyous. Trois quadrilles extrémement faciles., between 1845-1848, 1 score (7 pages); New York (N.Y.): A. A. Van-Gelder For piano. Dedicated to Mademoiselle Emilie Wandell by the editor. Title page illustration: a group of young children playing marbles as a dog scratches his ear nearby / lithographed by Lewis and Brown. (Box 2, Item 66)
  5 movements of the piece are labeled in the score as the following: No. 1. Pantalon, No. 2. Été, No. 3. Poule, No. 4. Pastourelle, No. 5. Finale.
- Openshaw, John Love sends a little gift of roses Love sends a little gift of roses: a ballad, 1919, 1 score (5 pages); New York (N.Y.): T. B. Harms For voice and piano. Lyricist: Cooke, Leslie (Box 2, Item 67)
- Phelps, E. S. Dream kisses Dream kisses: caprice for pianoforte, 1899, 1 score (7 pages); New York (N.Y.): Schroeder and Gunther For piano. Dedicated to Mr. Robert L. Fernald of Brooklyn, New York. Color title page illustration: title outlined by an oval frame of pink roses with green leaves. (Box 2, Item 68)
- Polla, William C., 1876-1939 If you would care for a lonely heart If you would care for a lonely heart = La tristess du coeur, 1919, 1 score (6 pages); Hartford (Conn.): C. C. Church and Company For voice and piano. Lyricist: Lamb, Arthur J., 1870-1928 Other title: Tristess du coeur Color title page illustration: a portrait of a woman decorated with pink roses / lithographed by Knapp Co. Inc. N.Y. Additional illustrations on verso of title page and back cover. (Box 2, Item 69)
- Purdy, W. T. (William Thomas), 1883-1918 On, Wisconsin! On, Wisconsin!: March song, 1910, 1 score (3 pages); Milwaukee (Wis.): Joseph Flanner For voice and piano. Lyricist: Beck, Carl, 1885-1963 Lyrics for the voice part do not have their own staff - they are written above the piano staves. Excerpts from Love's loyalty waltzes by Emil E. Tanner; Silver buckle "Rag" two-step by Jos. Sikorra; and "Dope," a rag novellettee two-step by W.C. Powell on p. [4] and p. [3] and [4] of cover. Color title page illustration: a man playing football in a uniform with red accents / illustrated by Carl Beck. (Box 2, Item 70)
- Richmond, Benjamin Dance of the honey bees Dance of the honey bee's, 1902, 1 score (5 pages); New York (N.Y.): Jos. W. Stern and Co. For piano. Dedicated to [his] brother Maurice Richmond. Title page illustration: honeybees dancing in lineups surrounding a king and queen honeybee. (Box 2, Item 71)
- Roberts, Lee S., 1884-1949 Smiles Smiles, 1918, 1 score (3 pages); Detroit (Mich.): Jerome H. Remick and Co. For voice and piano. Lyricist: Callahan, J. Will, 1874-1946 Color title page illustration: a portrait of a smiling woman with dark hair and red lips. (Box 2, Item 72)
- Romberg, Sigmund, 1887-1951 Student prince. Serenade; arranged Serenade solo [from] the student prince in Heidelberg, 1925, 1 score (5 pages); New York (N.Y.): Harms Inc. For voice and piano. Lyricist: Donnelly, Dorothy, 1880-1928 At head of title: The Messrs Shubert the Student prince of Heidelberg, a stupendous musical production. Other songs available from this production listed on title page. Color title page illustration: flowery filigree illuminating the title. (Box 2, Item 73)
- Romberg, Sigmund, 1887-1951 Maytime. Will you remember. Vocal score Will you remember (sweetheart), 1917, 1 score (6 pages); New York (N.Y.): G. Schirmer For two voices and piano. Lyricist: Young, Rida Johnson Duet parts are for female voice (Ottilie) and male voice (Dick). Color title page illustration: a woman carrying a large bouquet of green flowers and wearing a green skirt / Ray Van Buren. (Box 2, Item 74)
- Russell, Henry, 1812-1900 Fine old English gentleman Fine old English gentleman: a popular English ballad, circa 1835, 1 score (3 pages); New York (N.Y.): Atwill's Music Saloon For voice and piano. Other title: Old English gentleman Title page notes that the piece was originally sung by Mr. H. Russell. 2nd edition. Title page illustration: a man sitting with dogs at his feet while a banquet goes on in the background (Box 2, Item 75)
- Russell, Henry, 1812-1900 Rockaway Rockaway, or On old Long Island's sea-girt shore: a ballad, 1840, 1 score (5 pages); Boston (Mass.): Geo. P. Reed For voice and piano. Lyricist: Sharpe, Henry John Other title: On old Long Island's sea-girt shore Dedicated to Mrs. T. C. Grattan. Title page illustration: a beach with a ship at sea visible in the distance / lithographed by Bufford and Co. (Box 2, Item 76)
- Schaum, John W. (John Walter), 1905-1988 True blue lady True blue lady (a tribute to mother), 1945, 1 score (5 pages); New York (N.Y.): Belwin Inc. For voice and piano. Title page notes that the piece is a "piano solo with words". Color title page illustration: image based on James Whistler's Arrangement in Grey and black no. 1 (Whistler's mother) of a woman in a blue gown sitting in a chair. (Box 2, Item 77)
- Searing, J. H. Parodi mazurka Parodi mazurka or the Searing waltz: composed and taught by J. H. Searing at his private academy 56 Bond Street, 1851, 1 score (4 pages); New York (N.Y.): William Hall and Son For piano. Arranger: Brown, P. Other title: Searing waltz Dedicated to Signorina Teresa Parodi. Title page illustration: a couple dancing / lithographed by Sarony and Major. (Box 2, Item 78)
- Shaw, Oliver, 1779-1848 Gov. Wright's grand march Gov. Wright's grand march, 1844, 1 score (6 pages); Boston (Mass.): Oliver Ditson and Co. For piano. Bugle and ophiclyde solos indicated on music. "Composed and respectfully dedicated to His Excellency, Governor of New York". Color title page illustration: New York sate arms, with a shield showing the rising sun over a landscape with a canal bridge; below is the state motto "Excelsior." The shield is flanked by two classical figures: Justice (left) with scales and sword, and Hope holding an anchor and a scythe symbolizing agriculture. Above is an eagle holding arrows, olive branches, and a streamer reading "E Pluribus Unum" / F. F. Oakley's Lith. (Box 2, Item 79)
- Shaw, Oliver, 1779-1848 Kalamazoo polka brillante Kalamazoo: polka brillante, 1858, 1 score (5 pages); Boston (Mass.): Oliver Ditson and Co. For piano. Cordially inscribed to the Board of Trustees of the Michigan State Institution for the Insane. Color title page illustration: a scene of a building complex entitled "Michigan Asylum for the Insane" / lithographed by F. F. Oakley's. (Box 2, Item 80)
- Sherwood, E. H. (Edgar Harmon), b. 1845 Velocipede gallop New velocipede: song of the last sensation, 1869, 1 score (5 pages); Rochester (N.Y.): J. P. Shaw For piano. Addressed to Mercer and Monod, of New York. Dedicated to [his] friend W. T. Winsley. Title page illustration: a man riding a velocipede while another man watches in the background / Kingdon and Boyd. (Box 2, Item 81)
  Title page notes that this is one of two pieces available in this series, the other being Velocipede polka.
- Slade, Charles Thou hast learned to love another Thou hast learned to love another: ballad arranged for the piano forte, 1849, 1 score (5 pages); Boston (Mass.): Oliver Ditson and Co. For voice and piano. Title page illustration: a scene of the Oliver Ditson and Co. publisher building in Boston / lithographed by J. H. Bufford. (Box 2, Item 82)
- Széchényi, Imre, gróf, 1825-1898 Schnee-polka Schnee-polka: für das piano-forte, between 1854 and 1861, 1 score (5 pages); New York (N.Y.): C. Breusing For piano. Pages are out of order, and page 3 is missing. At head of title page: Der frau Metzler-Lutterot gewidmet. Title page illustration: a cottage in the mountains with scenery covered in snow. (Box 2, Item 83)
- Wade, Herman Avery I've got a pain in my sawdust I've got a pain in my sawdust, 1909, 1 score (5 pages); New York (N.Y.): Jos. W. Stern and Co. For voice and piano. Lyricist: Warner, Henry Edward Other title: Plaint of the little bisque doll Title page notes that the piece was "sung with Tremendous Success by Kitty Cheatham under the title 'The Plaint of the little bisque doll'". Dedicated to Miss Kitty Cheatham. Title page erroneously attributes lyrics to Henry C. Warner, a misprint of the lyricist's middle initial. Color title page illustration: a girl in a white dress leaning over a table with drawings and a doll in the background. (Box 2, Item 84)
- Wallace, William Vincent, 1812-1865 Lurline. Selections; arranged Lurline quadrilles, 1860, 1 score (10 pages); London (England): Cramer, Beale and Chappell For piano with cornet accompaniment. Arranger: Coote, Charles, 1809-1880 Other title: Quadrille Lurline Excerpts from William Vincent Wallace's opera, Lurline, arranged as quadrilles. Color title page illustration: a scene from William Vincent Wallace's opera, Lurline: Rudolph and Lurline at a feast on the banks of the Rhine river / lithographed by T. Packer; Stannard and Dixon. (Box 2, Item 85)
  No. 1. Pantalon: Sail, sail, on the midnight gale; Come away to the chase -- No. 2. Été: Overture; Sad as my soul; Gentle troubadour -- No. 3. Poule: Take this cup of sparkling wine; Flow on thou silver Rhine -- No. 4. Trenise: Now with joy; A father's love -- No. 5. Finale: Though the world with transport bless thee; Gentle troubadour; Oh thou to whom this heart.
- Wallerstein, A. (Anton), 1813-1892 Brigand polka Brigand polka, 1846, 1 score (5 pages); New York (N.Y.): William Hall and Son For piano. Title page illustration: a man and a woman in costume dancing / lithographed by Bufford and Co. (Box 2, Item 86)
- Warren, Charles Hail, glorious banner of our land Hail! Glorious banner of our land, 1861, 1 score (5 pages); Cincinnati (Ohio): John Church, Jr. For voice and piano. Inscribed to Major General George B. McClellan by Mrs. Mary Farrell Moore, Cincinnati, Ohio, July 4th 1861. Color title page illustration: female figure of Columbia holding an American flag, standing on an axe and wood bundle and in front of a bald eagle, with ships in the background / lithographed by Gibson and Co. (Box 2, Item 87)
- Weber, Carl Maria von, 1786-1826 Freischütz. Schaut, o schaut; arranged Wilt thou tempt the wave with me [from] Weber's Der Freischutz, 1825, 1 score (4 pages); London (England): Mayhew and Co. For two voices and piano. Lyricist: Van Dyk, Harry Stoe, 1798-1828 Arranger: Barnett, John, 1802-1890 Free arrangement of excerpts from the opera's finale for vocal duet with piano accompaniment with words by H. S. Van Dyk. Title page illustration: a man and woman walking by water with ship in background. (Box 2, Item 88)
- White, C. A. (Charles Albert), 1832-1892 Mother take me home again Three beautiful home songs: 2. mother, take me home again, 1870, 1 score (5 pages); Boston (Mass.): White, Smith and Perry For voice and piano. Lyricist: Smith, Dexter, 1842?-1909 Each page is bordered by a filigree frame. First page notes that the piece was originally sung by Rollin Howard. Title page illustration: a little girl kneeling in prayer amidst toys and shoes on the floor / lithographed by J. H. Bufford. (Box 2, Item 89)
  Title page notes that this is a three-piece series, and included is the second piece in the series only.
- Winner, Septimus, ǂd 1827-1902 Col. Ellsworth's funeral march Col. Ellsworth: funeral march, 1861, 1 score (5 pages); Philadelphia (Pa.): Lee and Walker For piano. Dedicated to Francis E. Brownell Esq. First page also erroneously attributes dedication to Francis C. Brownell, a misprint of the dedicatee's middle initial. Color title page illustration: portrait of Elmer Ephraim Ellsworth in uniform standing on an American flag. (Box 2, Item 90)
  Second title page includes text reading "I am perfectly content to accept whatever my fortune may be, confident that he who noteth even the fall of a sparrow, will have some purpose even in the fate of one like me.".
- Woodworth, Fannie S. Fiddle stick polka Fiddle stick polka, 1859, 1 score (5 pages); Buffalo (N.Y.): J. Sage and Sons For piano. Inscribed to Miss Georgia L. Houghton of Buffalo N. Y. Title page illustration: filigree illuminating title text (Box 2, Item 91)
- Zeuner, Charles, 1795-1857 New England Guards quick step New England Guards quick step, 1835, 1 score (2 pages); Boston (Mass.): John Ashton and Co. For piano. First page notes that the piece was originally performed by the Boston Brass Band. Dedicated to Capt. Thos. Dwight, the officers and members of the corps Title page illustration: New England Guards perform a military exercise in front of the Massachusetts State House / lithographed by Pendleton's. (Box 2, Item 92)
Search Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the Library's online catalog.
Subjects
Popular music; Piano music; Songs with piano; United States--History--Civil War, 1861-1865--Songs and music
Genres
sheet music; sheet music covers